KIM SUNDEEN

Full Stack Software Engineer | Mapper | Project Coordinator

% https://ksundeen.github.io ⊠kim.h.sundeen@gmail.com 📞 218.590.1330 💡 Duluth, MN

LIFE PHILOPHY "The only mistake is one from which you didn't learn" -A Friend



SUMMARY

Kim is an energetic & quick learner as full stack software engineer in the GIS landscape. With 12 years of experience architecting, developing, & implementing progressive full stack application solutions she always focuses on improving the end-user's experience & the back-end design & solution maintenance. Kim is an expert GIS database management, desktop, & mobile application development. She keeps her skills current by leading workshops, completing online training, & coordinating user groups.

LANGUAGES & TECHNOLOGIES

- Web development: Typescript, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript frameworks, PHP
- Code Versioning: Git, Github, Hg Mercurial, TortoiseSVN
- **OS**: Windows, Linux, Mac
- Server-side/desktop programming: Python, C# .NET, SQL/PLSQL
- Database design/structures: Microsoft SQL Server, 11g/12c Oracle, PostgreSQL, MySQL, MS Access, Excel
- ArcGIS Enterprise stack: ArcGIS Server, Web Adapter, ArcSDE, Portal, Data store
- Mapping APIs: Esri's JavaScript API 3.x, 4.x, Leaflet, Mapbox, Google Maps, Openlayers
- GIS/GPS/Mobile Apps: ArcGIS 9.x-10.x, ArcGIS Pro 2.x, QGIS 2-3, Google Earth KML, Garmin, ArcPad, Terrasync, & Pathfinder Office, Survey 123, ArcGIS for Collector, Web AppBuilder Developer Edition, ArcGIS Online

SOFT SKILLS

- Staff Supervision: Managed remote development teams for software development & database configuration using agile project management with RAMTeCH. Oversaw & trained student GIS technicians on GIS data entry procedures for UW Nursing School mapping projects & LTE staff for short-term land ownership projects with the Bad River Tribe.
- Agile Scrum Coaching: Lead two teams as scrum master for 10-member client software development team & internal projects for MN Power (3-person team).
- Workshop Presentations & Training: Taught introductory Python, JavaScript, GPS & GIS sessions for small group workshops on:

 (1) using new mapping & GPS programs
 (2) ArcGIS Desktop & opensource QGIS,
 (3) process for updating website front ends, &
 (4) GIS user needs & feasibility assessments,
 (5) Lead yearly workshops Esri's Utility Network Tools, Opensource GIS, & Jupyter Python notebooks (see full details: https://ksundeen.github.io/portfolio.html#media
- **Presentations & Graphic Design:** See my web-portfolio for examples: https://ksundeen.github.io/gallery.html; Awarded 1st Place: Large-format map, 2014 National Tribal GIS Conference, "A Bird's Eye View of the Bad River Watershed & Proposed Mine."
- Technical & Scientific Writing: Wrote & awarded \$127,000 FEMA grant, \$10,000 University of Wisconsin-Madison research grant,
 \$5,200 ESRI Conservation Grant Program grant. Published per-reviewed research articles on GIS, modeling, & wildlife research.

EDUCATION & CERTIFICATIONS

- 2019 2021 University of West Georgia, Applied Computer Science
 - o Focus: opensource GIS mobile disconnected editing of field data
- Continued Education: computer science, GIS, & web development courses through Lake Superior College, University of Wisconsin-Madison, FreeCodeCamp
 - Biking Route Finder (Google Maps API & Postgresql database to highlight optimal biking routes around Duluth based on the user's preference for terrain, slope, social media tweets, & proximity to bikes -https://ksundeen.github.io/assets/videos/CycleRoutesIntro small.mp4
- 2012 Certified Geographic Information Systems Professional (GISP) #84940
- 2012 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Graduate Certificate: Geographic Information Systems
 - Focus: geostatistical regression of remotely-sensed mercury concentrations & data science methods.
- 2011 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Master of Science: Conservation Biology & Sustainable Development
 - Focus: predictive spatial models to detect wildlife & electric distribution power line risks.
- 2006 University of Wisconsin-Madison, Bachelor of Science: Wildlife Ecology, Certificate: Environmental Studies

Kim H. Sundeen Page 1 of 3

PROJECT EXPERIENCE

- **Web Map App Development & Implementation:** Planned & developed custom ArcGIS web mapping applications & designed & trained on configuring Google Analytics web tracking for improving web marketing for:
 - Lake Superior Consulting engineering web viewers in Angular & C# frameworks using Esri's API 3.x,
 - o Bad River Tribal Ownership & Lease Viewer (ArcGIS Flex Viewer & SDE database),
 - City of Duluth Street Update Viewer (Esri's Web App Builder & SDE database),
 - MN Power's Electric Utility Asset Identification (Esris' JavaScript API & Web AppBuilder Developer's Edition & SDE database),
 - o Biking Route Finder (Google Maps API & Postgresql database).
- ArcGIS Service Publishing Automation: Developed configuration-driven python solution for other clients to quickly publish 20-40
 GIS web services between different development/staging/production environments through ArcMap into ArcGIS Server 10.6.
 This process saved 3-4 hours/day of manual error-prone service publishing. Created ArcGIS add-ins & published REST geoprocessing tools into ArcGIS Server to simplify City of Duluth's street & pavement updates for users.
- GIS Data Migration for Gas UPDM New Utility Network: Lead agile software development & project planning for client & consultant teams to customize python-plsql oracle database migration solutions to handle ETL from 5 source databases to one unified model. Managed multiple Esri alpha/beta software releases for changes in the new Utility Network model.
- GIS Workflow & Process Improvement: Coordinated GIS feasibility study to understand how users interact & use the applications. The results are used to develop clear tool requirements for Lake Superior Consulting app tool development. Documented workflows for engineering staff at City of Duluth to identify areas for improvement. Learned established GIS data entry policies.
- Full Cycle Project Development & Implementation: Coordinated GIS user needs assessment & implementation plans for 19 projects for software development, database development & improvements, training, & website enhancements for City of Duluth IT Dept. & Public Works & Utilities Dept. Priorities were used to direct funding to most important projects. Conducted GIS feasibility & UX/UI study for Lake Superior Consulting that clearly identified user, business, & technical requirements for 10 new development tools.
- **GIS Data Security:** Implemented new ArcGIS Server security protocol for publishing GIS services online; Researched & re-wrote external & internal data-sharing agreements & policies for the Bad River Tribe.

WORK EXPERIENCE

2018 – GIS Developer

Q Duluth, MN

present

Lake Superior Consulting – Software Development

- GIS Business Strategy Conducted GIS feasibility & UX/UI study that clearly identified user, business, & technical requirements
 for 10 new development tools. Lead clearly-defined research efforts & client presentations on implementing &
 architecting new mobile mapping systems that delivered immediate use for client projects with aggressive deadlines.
- **Team Leadership & Collaboration** Collaborated with clients & software engineers/IT professionals to improve knowledge transfer to increase & knowledge transfer within departments & gather better business requirements. My efforts reduced the time from idea to implemented solution from 2 months to 3 weeks.
- GIS App & Tool Development Engineered applications using Esri, SharePoint, Primavera, & SQL Server integrations used by over 200 users. Used web frameworks to align, extend, & develop existing tools & programs (Angular, TypeScript, jQuery), backend internal applications (MVVM, C#, .NET), & GIS tools (Python 2.7, 3.x, Leaflet's API, Esri's JavaScript API 3.x, 4.x).

2017-2018 GIS Analyst/Developer

Stillwater, MN (remote position)

RAMTeCH Software Solutions – Professional Services

- Redesigned Practices & Coached Clients in Agile Lead as Scum Master for 10-member team to re-architect client software development life cycle & direct funds for applications & tools. Lead general & detailed client-focused user-training/demos.
- Engineered Data Migration & ETL Software Tools for Clients Designed, built, tested, & released C#, Python & SQL gas & electric utility network migration toolsets accessing Oracle 11g/12g SDE databases, ArcMap & Pro desktop tools that seamlessly handled ETL from 5 source databases to one unified model for Esri's new Utility Network as 1st official Esri implementation.
- Developed & Presented AWS Workshops for Clients & Conferences Worked with MN GIS/LIS Consortium to use ArcGIS
 Enterprise software for gas, electric, water, & utility operators using virtual AWS production environments.

Kim H. Sundeen Page **2** of **3**

2016-2017 GIS Programmer Analyst



- Mobile Mapping Application/Survey Tool Development Developed, implemented, & trained staff on GIS services & geoprocessing tools through ArcGIS Server/ArcGIS Online for mobile data entry & data-transfer. Created Python routines to download & extract ArcGIS Online data & images from a Survey123 app & export to PDF with hyperlinked images & a summary of data from multiple related tables within a database. Developed MN Power's Electric Utility Asset Identification using Esri's JavaScript API & Web AppBuilder Developer's Edition & SDE database.
- Software Training & Developing Documentation Standards Trained staff on Esri's Model Builder, Python, & ArcGIS Online for
 utility edits, work order, & field tools systems. Documented publishing workflows in Survey123, ArcGIS Collector, & web maps.

2015-2016 GIS Specialist



City of Duluth - Engineering Division

- GIS Web Map Software Project Management Designed & managed a GIS user needs assessment & implementation for 19
 projects for software development, database development/improvements, & training for City of Duluth IT Department, Public
 Works, & Utilities. Developed City of Duluth Street Update Viewer web application.
- User Training & Presentations Lead monthly knowledge transfer user groups & designed new user training for new systems.
- Multiuser Database Management & Data Editing Edited gas, water, & storm GIS data in versioned SQL Server SDE databases.
 Expanded existing GIS map services to Python-built geoprocessing services to automate web map updates.

2012-2015 GIS Specialist



Bad River Tribe - Natural Resources Department

- Survey Field Collection, Processing, & Training Managed diverse field data collection preparation, training, pre- & post-processing for surveys on roads, historical properties, utilities, & tree inventories using Esri's ArcPad, in Trimble GeoXH series.
- Map Creation, Analysis, & Automation Designed & trained non-developers to use Python to manipulate, re-write, or edit
 raster/vector data for use in GIS analysis & remote sensing apps (image enhancements, transforms, & radiometric/atmospheric
 correction). Deployed Tribal Ownership & Lease Viewer (ArcGIS Flex Viewer & SDE database).
- Data Creation, Maintenance & Standardization for Natural Resources Website Designed GIS databases for all depts.,
 planned & published data-entry web maps, & updated tribal website. Added secured & public Google, Esri's JavaScript API,
 ArcGIS Online, & GeoMoose OpenLayers web maps. Implemented ArcGIS Server security protocol for REST services.

ACHIEVEMENTS

Notable Presentations & Workshops

- 2019. "Building, Branding, & Boosting your Web Portfolio with Github Pages & Google Analytics." Women in Tech Duluth User's Group, Feb.
- Sundeen, K.H. (2018). "Exploring the Utility Network in ArcGIS Pro for Water, Electric, & Gas Networks." MN GIS/LIS Fall Workshop, Oct.
- 2018. Sharing Code, Maps, & Data Science Through a Digital Jupyter Notebook." Duluth.NET Meetup group, June.
- 2017 & 2018. "Exploring the Utility Network in ArcGIS Pro." MN GIS/LIS Spring & Fall Workshop.
- 2017. Early Adopters of the Gas Utility Network: Are You the Tortoise or the Hare? Esri's GeoConX Conference, Sept.
- 2016. "Simplifying Metadata Editing for the Non-Programmer." Northern MN GIS User Group, April.
- 2016. "Designing a Long-Term GIS Vision & Implementation Plan." MN GIS/LIS Pre-Conference Workshop, Oct.
- 2015. "From the Field through the Firewall: An Approach to Streamlining Utility GIS Data Access in the Field, Office, & Web." MN GIS/LIS Conference, Oct.
- 2015. "Bringing Free & Open Source GIS to India Country." WI Land Information Association, Feb.

Organizations & Affiliations

- Director 2018-Present: Launched & Coordinate Duluth Women in Tech (WiT) groups to learn, present, & develop professionally.
- Co-coordinate .NET Duluth meetup groups for developers for presentations & professional development
- Conference Committee Member 2018: Minnesota GIS/LIS Conference, Virtual Environment Task Force
- Conference Committee Member 2016-2017: Minnesota GIS/LIS Conference, Workshop Committee
- Board of Directors 2014-2015: Wisconsin Land Information Association (WLIA), Chair of Membership Committee
- Committee Member 2014-2015: National Tribal Geographic Information Support Center (NTGISC), Publications Committee

Kim H. Sundeen Page 3 of 3

